Welcome to chapter 12. This chapter deals with kidney and urinary tract pathology.
We're going to begin with congenital lesions. These are relatively high yield because they
give us a chance to tie a little bit of embryology in with organ systems. And of course, that's
really a great way for examiners to go after embryology type questions in the context of
clinical scenarios. So the first disorder that we want to be familiar with is called a horseshoe
kidney. Now the idea here is that we get a conjoined kidney, usually at the lower pole,
and this is the most common congenital renal anomaly. Here's a picture of a horseshoe kidney,
and you can clearly see that this kidney obviously has the shape of a horseshoe. What is important,
however, is that this kidney is usually going to be located abnormally in the lower abdomen.
Now this becomes important because recall from embryology that the kidney is actually developed
in the pelvis, and then it ascends into the abdomen. Now imagine that as this kidney is trying to
ascend into the abdomen, it's going to get stuck on the root of the inferior mesenteric artery,
and so as it's trying to go up and it gets stuck on the root of the IMA, its ascension is going to be
blocked, and so this kidney will be abnormally located in the abdomen. The next congenital disorder
is renal agenesis. A means without, and genesis means production, so in this particular case there's an
absence of kidney formation. Now that absence of kidney formation can be unilateral or it can be
bilateral. In unilateral agenesis, the complication will be that the patient will be lacking one kidney,
and the consequence of that will be that the existing kidney will undergo hypertrophy. Now the existing
kidney, when it undergoes hypertrophy, is actually going to be doing the work of two kidneys.
That's not really a problem until many years down the line, and that's when hyperfiltration injury
will begin to lead to a risk of renal failure. In bilateral renal agenesis, there is lack of
formation of both kidneys, and if I had to summarize this in one word, I would summarize it with
oligohydramnios. Recall from embryology that the baby floats around in amniotic fluid, and that
amniotic fluid essentially is the baby's filtrate coming from the kidney, i.e. the baby's floating
around in its own urine. The consequence of having low amniotic fluid are multiple. Number one, the
fetus will develop lung hypoplasia. Go back and remind yourselves that when the lung develops
embryologically, one way by which it grows is by stretch, and so as the baby is in the womb, it's breathing
in and out amniotic fluid, and the breathing in of amniotic fluid stretches the lung, and when the
baby breathes out, that again causes collapse of the lung, and it's the stretching and the collapse
of the lung that actually allows for development of the lung to occur. So you can imagine that if there
isn't enough amniotic fluid, the lung will not be expanded appropriately, and therefore the lung will
undergo hypoplasia, and so one consequence of having bilateral renal agenesis is lung hypoplasia.
Another consequence is that there will be a flat face with low-set ears, and the way I think about this is
that normally the baby's in a bubble, and it's floating around in amniotic fluid. However, if the amniotic fluid
is low or lacking, then the face will get pressed up against the wall of the uterus, and if the face gets pressed
up against the wall of the uterus, for example, then that will result in a flat face with low-set ears.
And finally, there can also be a risk of developmental defects of the extremities. Same consequence, the extremities
normally require that bubble of amniotic fluid to develop properly, but here they're going to be
pressed up against mom's tissue, and when they're pressed up against mom, that's going to result in
developmental defects of the extremities. This entire sequence, hypoplasia of the lung, flat face with
low-set ears, and developmental defects of the extremities, this whole sequence is called Potter sequence,
and that's something to be familiar with. Again, it goes back to embryology. Bilateral renal
agenesis is incompatible with life. However, when an examination of the fetus was done, we'd see the
classic findings of Potter sequence, very high yield because it ties into embryology. Here's a picture of
a fetus with Potter sequence. There's flattening of the face with low-set ears, and then some extremity
defects as well. Again, high yield to remember that these are all a consequence of oligohydramnios.
The next of the congenital defects is actually going to be kicking off a little bit of a theme.
Now, what we want to discuss as we move forward are some congenital defects that result in cyst
formation in the kidney, and there's a few of them. The first of them is dysplastic kidney. The idea
here is that you have a non-inherited, and that's important, congenital malformation of the
renal parenchyma that's characterized by cysts with abnormal tissue. Now, basically, these patients
develop cysts within their kidney. However, this is not inherited. The cysts are characterized by
abnormal tissue, especially cartilage. Here's a picture of an example where we've got a cystic
space, and that cystic space is lined by a wall, and within that wall, we can clearly see that there
is cartilage. Dysplastic kidney is actually not inherited, and that's important because if a fetus
has dysplastic kidney, and we asked the question, what's the risk of developing a similar dysplastic
kidney in a subsequent pregnancy, the risk would be relatively low because, again, this is not an inherited
disorder. Now, clinically, this is usually unilateral. However, on examinations, it's usually
bilateral, and the reason it's usually bilateral on examinations is because they like to try to confuse
you with inherited polycystic kidney disease. I think every medical student, when they hear about
cysts in the kidney, the first thing that comes to their mind is polycystic kidney disease. However,
it is important to note that there are other diseases that can also cause cysts in the kidney,
and so examiners like to go after them to see if they can get you to knee-jerk and select
polycystic kidney disease to see whether you really understand the spectrum of what can happen
within the kidney. The next of the cystic diseases of the kidney is polycystic kidney disease,
also known as PKD. This is an inherited defect, and it always results in bilateral enlargement of the
kidneys. The reason that the kidneys are enlarged is that the patients get cysts in both the renal cortex
and the medulla, and that's important to note. Again, inherited defect, bilateral, with cysts in the
renal cortex and the medulla. Now, when you look at a picture of polycystic kidney disease, you clearly see
that there is cyst formation and that the kidney is enlarged. So both kidneys, again, will be enlarged.
Now, polycystic kidney disease can actually be divided into two subtypes. There's an autosomal recessive form
and an autosomal dominant form. The autosomal recessive form classically used to be called the juvenile form,
and that's because it usually presents in infants. It presents with renal failure and hypertension,
and newborns can present with the Potter sequence, very high yield. Imagine if a patient has autosomal
recessive polycystic kidney disease, and it's so severe that the kidney isn't functioning. It's as if
they have bilateral renal agenesis. Again, the kidneys would not be producing fluid, and hence there would be
oligohydramnios with all of the resultant consequences of oligohydramnios, i.e. Potter
sequence. The associations of polycystic kidney disease are also important to know, and in an autosomal
recessive form, it'll be associated with congenital hepatic fibrosis and hepatic cysts. The way I think
about this is that the patients get cysts in the kidney and cysts in the liver, and that the cysts in
the liver can result in congenital hepatic fibrosis. The presenting sign of this congenital hepatic
fibrosis will be that the patients will have signs and symptoms of portal hypertension. So when you have
a baby with signs and symptoms of portal hypertension, think about autosomal recessive polycystic kidney
disease. The additional form of polycystic kidney disease is autosomal dominant form, and the autosomal
dominant form presents in young adults. Some people like to use the mnemonic ADULT. So the AD is
autosomal dominant, and it's also the first two letters of adult. So this presents in young adults.
Now, the defect is actually present in the fetus at the time of birth, so it's due to a mutation in
adult polycystic kidney disease gene 1 or adult polycystic kidney disease gene 2. But the cysts,
they develop over time. And since the cysts develop over time, these patients will present
as adults. The way by which they present is hypertension, hematuria, and worsening renal failure.
The hypertension is usually due to an increased renin, so that these patients will also have an
increased plasma renin. There are some associations to be aware of in this particular form of polycystic
kidney disease, and they include bary aneurysms, hepatic cysts, and mitral valve prolapse. And the
bary aneurysms are particularly important because they are a cause of death in this particular subgroup
of patients. So if you have a clinical vignette, for example, in which you're told that there is a
family history of renal disease, and there is death occurring because of renal disease or brain
hemorrhage in, for example, the grandfather or the great grandfather, then you really want to put two
and two together and think about autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease. The way I have my
students remember this is that they get cysts in the liver, cysts in the brain, and cysts in the kidney.
Now, what do I mean by that? Well, the cysts in the kidney are the cysts of polycystic kidney disease.
The cysts in the brain is a cystic dilatation of a blood vessel in the brain. And remember that
bary aneurysms are basically balloon-like dilatations of a blood vessel in the brain. So you can think
about it as quote unquote a cyst. Additionally, they get hepatic cysts or cysts in the liver.
The last of the associations to be familiar with is mitral valve prolapse, and these patients can also
have mitral valve prolapse. And again, mitral valve prolapse can rarely be a cause of death as well.
The final of the cystic diseases and congenital diseases that we want to discuss is medullary
cystic kidney disease. Now, what's important here is, again, this is an inherited defect.
There are cysts in the kidney. However, the cysts are in the medullary collecting ducts of the kidney,
hence the name medullary cystic kidney disease. So that's one key distinction from polycystic kidney
disease is that here the cysts would be in the medullary collecting ducts. A second important
distinction from polycystic kidney disease is the fact that these patients have shrunken kidneys.
Now remember that in polycystic kidney disease, whether it be adult form or juvenile form,
the kidneys will be enlarged. However, in medullary cystic kidney disease, the kidneys are shrunken
and the patients will present with worsening renal failure. So again, shrunken kidneys with cysts in
the medulla of the kidney. And that concludes our congenital section. We're now going to move on to
acute renal failure.